Egbert Benson Collection
Egbert Benson Collection
1786-1819
Benson, Egbert, 1746-1833.
10 items (SC)
Papers of the Congressman, jurist, and New York State Attorney General; includes outgoing letters to Samuel Bayard, Samuel M. Hopkins, Nicholas Low, William S. Shaw, and a single incoming item from John Jay.
149173
Biographical History
1746 Born in New York City on June 21, 1746
1765 Graduated from King’s College (Columbia University)
1777 Appointed first Attorney General of New York Served as a member of the State Assembly
1784 Appointed Associate Judge of the Supreme Court of New York
1784 Selected as a member of the Continental Congress
1787 Selected as a member of the Continental Congress
1788 Selected as a member of the State Constitutional Convention (ratified Federal Constitution) Selected as a member of the Continental Congress
1789 Elected to the First United States Congress
1791 Elected to the Second United States Congress
1801 Appointed Judge of the United States Circuit Court, second circuit
1804 Appointed First President of the New-York Historical Society
1813 Elected to the Thirteenth Congress (resigned August 2, 1813)
1833 Died in Jamaica, New York on August 2, 1813
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Egbert Benson Collection consists of 9 items of Correspondence and a single item of Miscellany, all of which were generated between 1786 and 1819, although a number of the letters are undated. The outgoing Correspondence of the first Attorney General of New York State, delegate to the Annapolis Convention, and Congressman is mainly concerned with legal business (Samuel Bayard, Samuel M. Hopkins, William S. Shaw), although a few of the letters discuss politics or personal (John R. Madison) and financial matters. The single item of incoming correspondence, a letter from John Jay, is not the strident appeal of one Revolutionary leader to another, but the plea of a concerned son for news about the welfare of his ailing parent and his family:
There seems to be a spell on the Penns of my Friends of New York. Except Livingston, I have not had a line from other of them since I left America - not even from other of my Brothers - nor from you who are several Letters in my Debt.
I have a Favor to ask of you - it is that you would make a visit to my Father, and send me a minute account of his Health and that of the Family - make half a dozen Copies of your Letter, and send them and other to some Friend at Boston, or to Mr. Robt. Morris at Philadelphia to be forwarded in different vessels - do not neglect to do me this friendly office. You can easily conceive how painful it is to be so long in Ignorance and Suspence [sic] about the Situation and Welfare of Persons, so near and dear to one as many of those to whom I alluded, are to me.
In addition to the correspondence is an item of Miscellany, a receipt signed by Benson for payment of his salary.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains two series: Correspondence, which is arranged alphabetically, and Miscellany.
Subject and Genre Headings
Bayard, Samuel, 1767-1840.; Benson, Egbert, 1746-1833.; Hopkins, Samuel M. (Samuel Miles), 1772-1837.; Jay, John, 1745-1829.; Low, Nicholas, 1739-1826.; Shaw, William Smith, 1778-1826.; Attorneys general -- New York (State); Justice, Administration of -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Lawyers.; New York State; Politics, government and public administration
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Bayard, Samuel, undated; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 98)
  - Hopkins, Samuel Miles, 2 Jul 1811; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 98)
  - Jay, John, undated; 1 incoming letter (Sc 98)
  - Low, Nicholas, 25 Aug 1799; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 98)
  - Madison, John, 10 Dec 1819; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 98)
  - Shaw, William Smith, 13 Oct 1808; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 98)
  - Unidentified, 18 Feb 1786; 1 outgoing letter (Sc 98)
  - Unidentified, undated; 2 outgoing letters (Sc 98)
- Miscellany
  - Receipt for Benson's salary, 22 Jul 1789 (Sc 98)